Yesterday, out of nowhere, Amazon
released its own AI IDE named Kira. Yet
another VS Code fork that will compete
for the hearts and minds of programmers
alongside editors like Cursor, Windsor,
Firebase Studio, and Copilot, just to
name a few. It's powered by Claude
Sonnet 4.0, but claims to be better at
handling complexity than these other
sloppy tools thanks to an approach
called specdriven development. And right
now, it's free to use. But that's not
the only good news for developers. The
Chinese just dropped Kimmy K2, an openw
weight agentic coding model that
approaches the performance of Claude.
These tools are so powerful they might
even be able to fix pirate software's
code is so the entire internet can
finally stop dunking on this guy. In
today's video, we'll try out Amazon Curo
to find out if it truly is the cursor
co-pilot killer. It is July 16th, 2025,
and you're watching the Code Report. You
might remember a few weeks ago when
OpenAI was going to buy that other VS
Code fork, Windsor, for billions of
dollars. Well, that deal fell apart.
Then Google came in and gutted all the
talent from the company by convincing
them to abandon ship and join Google for
$2.4 billion. That screwed over many of
the employees at Windsurf, but it's not
a total loss because then Cognition, the
creator of Devon, is swooped in after
Google to buy up all the scraps in what
appears to be an all stock deal. We live
in a world where people will literally
pay you billions of dollars for a VS
Code fork because all these companies
are desperate to get developers to use
their products. But the company taking
the lion's share of developer money is
anthropic. primarily thanks to its Cloud
Code CLI tool. Anthropic went from less
than a billion in revenue last year to
now over 4 billion this year. And one of
their biggest investors is Amazon, which
has pumped $8 billion into the company
so far. Now, if you don't use Claude
code, there's a good chance you use an
IDE like Cursor powered by Claude
instead. It's great, but the problem is
that Anthropic has cursor by the balls.
If developers want to use Claude, Cursor
needs to act as a middleman and price it
in a way that can eventually become
profitable. Recently, Curser tried to
make some tweaks to its pricing that
caught some customers offguard because
suddenly their vibe coding bill became
way higher and Curser had to later come
out and apologize publicly. If that
weren't bad enough, now here comes Curo.
It's also a VS Code fork with many
similar features and based on its
initial pricing, it looks like you'll be
able to get much more out of Claude for
a much lower price. I'm sure it's a
total coincidence that Amazon chose to
release Kira right now, but let's try it
out and find out if it's any good.
Overall, I think the UI looks really
nice, but it did feel a bit slow and was
missing small features like chat
checkpoints and cursor. I also ran into
a bunch of delays because the service
was overloaded. But these are issues you
would expect on an early release product
like this. The biggest difference though
is that Kira tries to prevent you from
generating a bunch of slop all at once.
Rather than go straight to code, it
encourages you to start in this
requirements MD file, which defines
things like the user story and
acceptance conditions. Then once that
plan is in place, it can move on to the
design which is the design document that
outlines implementation details like
your component structure, your testing
strategy, error handling strategy and so
on. And then finally, those two
documents get combined together to
create an implementation plan. Each task
will outline the code the AI should
write. Then you can click this button in
the IDE to start it. Overall, the
process felt a bit slower, but it does
feel like a much more sane approach if
you're building something serious or
working with a team of multiple people.
Overall, it feels like an IDE designed
to appeal to developers working in
enterprise where things like design
documents and consistent code quality
matters. Currently, Kira is closed
source and only powered by Claude, but
in the future, they plan to offer other
models. Right now, Amazon is offering it
for free, so using it's a no-brainer,
but only time will tell if it becomes a
legit cursor killer. But if you want to
harness the full power of AI, you need
to understand the math and computer
science behind it. And you can do that
today for free with Brilliant, the
sponsor of today's video. Their how AI
works course teaches you how to build a
functioning language model from scratch
and lets you experiment with things like
feature vectors to edit facial
expressions and images. This hands-on
approach to learning helps you master
challenging concepts over time and is
proven to be six times more effective
than watching video lectures. Try
everything Brilliant has to offer for
free for 30 days by visiting
brilliant.org/fireship
or scan the QR code on screen to get 20%
off an annual premium subscription. This
has been the code report. Thanks for
watching and I will see you in the next